Guide to the Henry J. Oosting Papers, 1919-1968 UA.29.02.0021
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Henry J. Oosting papers
1919-1968
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Oosting, Henry J. (Henry John), 1903-1968
UA.29.02.0021
7 Linear Feet
Correspondence, field notes, writings,photographs and other subject files of Henry J. Oosting, Professor of Botany and Chairman of the Department of Botany at Duke University from 1931 to 1962. Major subjects include the ecology of virgin forests, vegetation on bare rocks, maritime vegetation in the Southeastern United States, North Carolina vegetation, the 1937 Louise A. Boyd expedition to Greenland with the American Geographical Society, the Victory Garden project in Durham, N.C., the Ecological Society of America, and the serial Ecological Monographs.
Alternative Format Available
As of October 2014, preservation-quality digital copies of the nitrate negatives are stored at: \cx4-fe-nas01.oit.duke.edu\Tucasi_cifs2\dpc-archive\Archived_NoAccess\na_OOS
Access Restrictions
Nitrate negatives are restricted and cannot be accessed without prior approval of the University Archivist. Most images have corresponding prints in the collection and all have been digitized. Please contact Research Services for more information.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Stored off-site; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Acquisitions Information
Received from Department of Botany, May 26, 1994. Accession UA2007-0019 was received in June 2007 from former professor Dwight Billings. The diary was gifted in 1993.
Biographical Note
Henry John Oosting, Professor of Botany and Chairman of the Department of Botany, worked at Duke University from 1931 to 1962. He was born March 12, 1903 in Holland, Michigan to John H. and Minna Oosting. He earned an A.B. from Hope College in 1925, an M.S. from Michigan State College in 1927, and a Ph.D. from the University of Minnesota in 1931. Oosting joined the faculty of the Department of Botany at Duke University in 1931, and later served as Chairman of the Department. His research interests included the ecology of virgin forests, vegetation on bare rocks, maritime vegetation in the Southeastern United States, and North Carolina vegetation. In 1937, he served as ecologist for the Louise A. Boyd expedition to Greenland with the American Geographical Society, and he directed the Victory Garden project in Durham, N.C. in 1943. Oosting actively participated in the Ecological Society of America and edited the serial Ecological Monographs. Oosting retired from Duke University around 1962; he died on October 30, 1968.
Scope and Content Note
The papers include correspondence, field notes, and other research notes of Henry J. Oosting. The collection is representative of Oosting's research in forest ecology, vegetation on bare rocks, and plants of North Carolina. The papers also document his participation in the 1937 Louise A. Boyd Expedition to Greenland, his participation in the governance and research of the Highlands Biological Station (Highlands, N.C.), and his participation in the Ecological Society of America. Much of the correspondence is between Oosting and colleagues at Duke University, including H. L. Blomquist and Lewis R. Anderson; colleagues throughout the United States; and former graduate students. Other files include family correspondence, as well as reports and correspondence from the Duke University Research Council, 1949-1963.
In June 2007, accession UA2007-0019 was added to the collection. This accession includes photographs from the 1937 Louise A. Boyd Expedition to Greenland. Subjects featured are glaciers; Kjerulf Fjord; Tromso, Norway; Jan Mayen Island; Cape Alfred; Clavering Isle; landscape; and native plants. In addition to the individual photos there are also six annotated photo posters. Photos are by Louise A. Boyd. Also included is Oosting's diary. The diary includes his reactions and observations about his travel to Eastern Greenland and return through England during the summer of 1937 on the Louise A. Boyd Expedition.
Nitrate negatives have been scanned and are available online. The original nitrate negatives are not available for use in the reading room.
Plants -- North Carolina; Oosting, Henry J. (Henry John), 1903-1968
- Correspondence, 1919-1968
  - A: Miscellaneous, 1959, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Peter H. Allen, 1956-1968 (Box 1)
  - Lewis E. Anderson, 1933-1965 (Box 1)
  - Nellie Beetham, 1956-1966 (Box 1)
  - Larry Carroll Bliss, 1953-1967 (Box 1)
  - H. L. Blomquist, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Clair Brown, 1940 (Box 1)
  - D. M. Brown, 1953 (Box 1)
  - M. Buell, 1961-1967 (Box 1)
  - C: Miscellaneous, 1936-1961, 1968 (Box 1)
  - S. A. Cain, 1958 (Box 1)
  - W. H. Camp, 1952 (Box 1)
  - John Cantlon, 1953, 1965 (Box 1)
  - J. E. Coaldrake, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - E. Lendell Cockrum, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Charles Cooper, 1957-1967 (Box 1)
  - W. S. Cooper, 1931-1966 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Don Correll, 1935-1957 (Box 1)
  - W. L. Culberson, 1952-1962 (Box 1)
  - D: Miscellaneous, 1962, 1965, 1966 (Box 1)
  - P. Dansereau, 1960 (Box 1)
  - John Darling, 1963 (Box 1)
  - J. H. Davis, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Department of the Army, 1967 (Box 1)
  - W. B. Drew, 1940-1962 (Box 1)
  - Duke University, 1932-1961 (Box 1)
  - E: Miscellaneous, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Frank Egler, 1940-1961 (Box 1)
  - F: Miscellaneous, 1950, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Knut Faegri, 1960-1963 (Box 1)
  - Hugo Ferchau, 1956-1967 (Box 1)
  - Edward Flaccus, 1955-1968 (Box 1)
  - R. F. Flint, 1937-1946 (Box 1)
  - Richard T. Forman, 1959-1966 (Box 1)
  - W. H. Freeman and Co., 1946-1968 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - G: Miscellaneous, 1953-1954, 1960, 1965, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Wendell Gauger, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Ben F. Graham, 1954-1964 (Box 1)
  - Great Lakes Colleges Association, 1962 (Box 1)
  - H: Miscellaneous, 1965, 1967, 1968 (Box 1)
  - R. M. Harper, 1939-1959 (Box 1)
  - Dexter W. Hess, 1952-1962 (Box 1)
  - Highlands Biological Station Executive Committee, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - N. Hotchkiss, 1929-1944 (Box 1)
  - R. R. Humphrey, 1932-1954 (Box 1)
  - Mary Humphreys, 1936-1964 (Box 1)
  - I: Miscellaneous, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - J: Miscellaneous, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Johnsen, Jr., 1955-1962 (surname spelled with an "e" and not "o") (Box 1)
  - Philip L. Johnson, 1957-1966 (Box 1)
  - K: Miscellaneous, 1961-1963, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Catherine Keever, 1957-1964 (Box 1)
  - Charles Kettering, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Lionel Klikoff, 1959-1967 (Box 1)
  - President Douglas Knight, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Jan Kornas, 1960-1966 (Box 1)
  - Norman E. Kowal, 1958-1968 (Box 1)
  - L: Miscellaneous, 1953-1961, 1968 (Box 1)
  - George LaRoi, 1958-1968 (Box 1)
  - Robert M. Linn, 1951-1967 (Box 1)
  - R. B. Livingston, 1940-1968 (Box 1)
  - M: Miscellaneous, 1962, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Alan F. Mark, 1958-1968 (Box 1)
  - J. W. Marr, 1952-1956 (Box 1)
  - James S. Martin, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - James McCleary, 1960-1968 (Box 1)
  - R. E. McDermott, 1954-1964 (Box 1)
  - Cal McMillan, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Rogers McVaugh, 1935-1957 (Box 1)
  - Harold Mooney, 1959-1966 (Box 1)
  - T. B. Mowbray, 1963-1968 (Box 1)
  - Walter F. Mueggler, 1957-1961 (Box 1)
  - N: Miscellaneous, 1961-1963, 1968 (Box 1)
  - National Geographic Magazine, 1963 (Box 1)
  - The Nature Conservancy, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Aubrey W. Naylor, 1958, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Daniel Norris, 1955-1961 (Box 1)
  - O: Miscellaneous, 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Charles E. Olmstead, 1942-1945 (Box 2)
  - Jan Kurt Oosting, 1939-1968 (Box 2)
  - Joy Oosting, 1942-1955 (Box 2)
  - Melvin Oosting, 1933-1940, undated (Box 2)
  - Lauce Oosting, 1932-1937 (Box 2)
  - William Owsley, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - P: Miscellaneous, 1962, 1968 (Box 2)
  - S. C. Pandeya, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Duncan Patten, 1958-1965 (Box 2)
  - E. Gibbes Patton, 1953-1966 (Box 2)
  - Jane Philpott, 1956-1961 (Box 2)
  - R. B. Platt, 1952-1967 (Box 2)
  - Nicholas Polunin, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Robert W. Powell, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - F. W. Preston, 1953-1966, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Elsie Quarterman, 1953-1967 (Box 2)
  - R: Miscellaneous, 1935-1962, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Patricia Raff, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Patricia Rand, 1962-1966 (Box 2)
  - Allen Rebuck, 1952-1966 (Box 2)
  - J. F. Reed, 1934-1968 (Box 2)
  - Richard Rhoades, 1961-1967 (Box 2)
  - Patricia Roberts, 1954-1962 (Box 2)
  - S: Miscellaneous, 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Wilf Schofield, 1956-1961 (Box 2)
  - R. M. Schuster, 1954-1962 (Box 2)
  - A. J. Sharp, 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - Napier Shelton, 1960-1964 (Box 2)
  - John P. Shontz, 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - Ben Smith, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Harold St. John, 1940-1941, 1945 (Box 2)
  - W. C. Steere, 1949, 1952 (Box 2)
  - A. D. Stoesz, 1931-1956 (Box 2)
  - T: Miscellaneous, 1919, 1948 (Box 2)
  - A. Tamsalu, 1953, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Oswald Tippo, 1959 (Box 2)
  - U: Miscellaneous, 1967 (Box 2)
  - V: Miscellaneous, 1928-1967 (Box 2)
  - Olli Vaartaja, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Dr. H. P. van der Schyff, 1960 (Box 2)
  - J. J. van Wyck, 1960-1967 (Box 2)
  - V. Eugene Vivian, 1962-1967 (Box 2)
  - W: Miscellaneous, 1966, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Richard Wagner, 1955-1966 (Box 2)
  - P. F. Wareing, 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - John Warren, 1954-1964 (Box 2)
  - A. Lincoln Washburn, 1937-1946 (Box 2)
  - T. E. Weier, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Bruce Welch, 1959-1966 (Box 2)
  - B. W. Wells, 1932-1954 (Box 2)
  - Philip Wells, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
  - George Woodwell, 1953-1967 (Box 2)
  - Charley Wu, 1957-1958 (Box 2)
  - John Yarborough, 1966, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Fredrick F. Yonkman, 1945, 1954 (Box 2)
  - H. E. Young, 1959-1968 (Box 2)
- Subject files, 1924-1967
  - Beaufort, 1947 Summer (Box 2)
  - Botany Seminar on NC Vegetation, 1949 (Box 2)
  - Botany Space Committee (Duke), 1965 (Box 2)
  - Classroom Materials, 1962-1964 (Box 2)
  - J. P. Decker, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Duke Forest: Checklist, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Duke Insurance, 1966 Mar. 25 (Box 2)
  - East Campus Ad Hoc Committee, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Ecological Society, 1957, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Field Botany Class for High School Teachers, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - M. L. Grant Photographs of Hawaii, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Grass Ecology, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Highlands Biological Station, 1957-1961 (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Highlands Biological Station: Research Committee, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Highlands Biological Station: Gorge Grant, 1960-1964 (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Highlands Biological Station: Trustees, General Information, 1960-1965 (Box 3)
  - Lake Junaluska, 1934-1939 (Box 3)
  - Michigan State Sem. Bot., 1955 (Box 3)
  - Michigan State Surface Formation Map, 1924 (Box 3)
  - National Science Foundation Application/Grant on Venus Fly-Trap, 1955-1958 (Box 3)
  - National Science Foundation Grant on Venus Fly-Trap Photographs, circa 1957-1958 (Box 3)
  - National Science Foundation Proposal for Gorge Research, 1963-1964 (Box 3)
  - National Science Foundation, 1967 (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Natural Area Committee of Duke Univ., 1959-1963 (Box 3)
  - N. C. Academy of Science, 1966 (Box 3)
  - New Hampshire, Univ. of, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
  - Personal Data (CV, etc.) (Box 3)
  - Pocomoke Swamp [Delaware] Photographs, undated (Box 3)
  - Research Council (Duke), 1949-1958 (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Research Council (Duke), 1958-1963 (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Scientific Writing, 1960s (Box 3)
  - V. N. Sukachev, 1961-1962 (Box 3)
  - TIAA/CREF, 1953 (Box 3)
  - World of Nature Series, 1964-1967 (Box 3)
- Research files, 1930-1967, undated
  - Ham Lake: Soil Samples, 1930 (Box 3)
  - Photographs of Unidentified Research Trips (includes images of Oosting and colleagues), circa 1930s (Box 3)
  - Potamogeton [Michigan], circa 1931 (Box 3)
  - Ham Lake: Soil and Mud Samples, circa 1932 (Box 3)
  - Ham Lake, circa 1933 (Box 3)
  - Pilot Mountain, 1934, 1942 (Box 3)
  - Atmometer and Soil, 1936 (Box 3)
  - Soil Moisture, 1936 (Box 3)
  - Jonathan Creek, 1936 June 26 (Box 3)
  - Field Ecology (Itasca), circa 1936 (Box 3)
  - Research Ideas: Problems, 1938, undated (Box 3)
  - Wyoming Timberline (with photographs), 1948 (Box 3)
  - Wyoming - Timberline (RESTRICTED: nitrate negatives) (Box 6)
  - Wyoming Photographs, circa 1948 (Box 3)
  - Wyoming (RESTRICTED: nitrate negatives), circa 1948 (Box 6)
  - Southeastern Conifers, circa early 1940s (Box 3)
  - Burn Study: New Hope Creek, 1940-1967 (Box 3)
  - Transpiration, 1942 (Box 3)
  - Transect Study: Soil Moisture, 1944-1945 (Box 3)
  - Spruce-Fir-Medicine Bows, circa 1948-1949 (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Spruce-Fir-Medicine Bows Photographs, circa 1948-1949 (Box 3)
  - White Pine, Blue Ridge Parkway, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Seedling Environment, 1951 (Box 3)
  - Turkey Oak, 1952 (Box 3)
  - Field Notes for Joyce Kilmer Forest Study (with photographs), 1953-1956 (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Maritime Forest Data (with photographs), circa 1955 (Box 4)
  - Hydrobiology Reading Notes, undated (Box 4)
  - Pulpwood Data [Maine], undated (Box 4)
  - Pulpwood Data [Maine] Photographs, undated (Box 4)
  - Pulpwood Data (RESTRICTED: nitrate negatives) (7 sleeves) (Box 6)
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 4)
  - Piedmont Review for Botany Rev., undated (Box 4)
- Writings, circa 1930-circa 1960s, undated
  - "Physical-Chemical Variables in a Minnesota Lake," circa 1930-1931 (Box 4)
  - "A Limnological Study of Ham Lake with Special Emphasis Upon the Flowering Plants," 1931 June (Box 4)
  - "Distribution of the Genus Potamogeton in Michigan," 1931 (Box 4)
  - "Distribution of Aquatic Flowering Plants in Relation to the Substratum," circa 1932-1933 (Box 4)
  - "Ecology in Relation to Botany in General," 1950 (Box 4)
  - "Ecological Processes and Vegetation of the Maritime Strand in the Southeastern United States," 1953-1954 (Box 4)
  - "The Maritime Live Oak Forest in NC," (with Philippe F. Bourdeau) (with photographs), 1958, 1959 (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - "Responses of Venus Fly Trap (Dionea Muscipula) to Factors Involved in Its Endemism," (with Patricia Roberts), circa 1958 (Box 4)
  - Outlines for talks, circa 1960s (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Book Manuscript (rough, for 2nd edition), "The Study of Plant Communities," undated (9 folders) (Box 4)
  - Sampling, undated (Box 4)
  - List of Publications from 1932-1958 (Box 4)
  - "A Guide to the Spring and Early Summer Flora of the Piedmont, North Carolina" by H. L. Blomquist and H. J. Oosting, 1936 (Box 7)
  - "A Guide to the Spring and Early Summer Flora of the Piedmont, North Carolina" by H. L. Blomquist and H. J. Oosting, 1940 (Box 7)
  - "A Guide to the Spring and Early Summer Flora of the Piedmont, North Carolina" by H. L. Blomquist and H. J. Oosting, 1948 (Box 7)
- Writings and research, 1940-1955, undated
  Scope and Contents note
  This series title applies to folders which contained both research notes and writings.
  - "Buried Viable Sees in a Sucessional Series of Olf Field and Forest Soils," (with Mary E. Humphreys), 1940 (Box 4)
  - "The Establishment of a White Birch Community on Cutover Pulpwood Land in Northwestern Maine," (with John Reed), 1942 (Box 4)
  - "Survival of Pine and Hardwood Seedlings in Forest and Open," (with P. J. Kramer and C. F. Korstian) (with photographs and negatives), 1952 (Box 4)
  - "Microclimate and a Relic Stand of Tsuga Canadensis in the Lower Piedmont of North Carolina," (with D. W. Hess) (with photographs and negatives), 1955 (Box 4)
  - "Tolerance to Salt Spray of Plants of Coastal Dunes," undated (Box 4)
- Greenland expedition, 1936-1941
  - Correspondence: Louise Boyd, 1937-1941 (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Photographs (contact prints): Images taken by Louise Boyd, 1937 (3 of 4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Photographs (contact prints): Images taken by Louise Boyd, 1937 (1 of 4 folders) (Box 5)
  - Photographs of Moss Rings on Jan Mayen Island taken by Louise Boyd on her Artic Expedition, 1937; Letter, 1938 Apr. 15 (Box 5)
  - Henry Oosting's Diary, 1937 Summer (Box 5)
  - Photographs by Henry Oosting and Others, 1937 (Box 5)
  - Nitrate negatives (RESTRICTED), 1937 (16 sleeves) (Box 6)
  - Notes and Records, 1937 (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Notes and Writings, 1937 (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Printed Material and Maps, 1936; Miscellaneous Items, 1937 (Box 5)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1937 (Box 5)
  - Clippings, 1937 (Box 5)
  - Handmade Poster featuring Print Photographs with Identification, 1937 (loose prints were placed in an archival photograph sleeve) (Oversize-folder 1)